Guide to the Spider Martin photographs, 1965, 1968 RL.11866
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Spider Martin photographs
1965, 1968
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Martin, Spider, 1939-2003
RL.11866
1 Linear Feet 2 boxes 44 photographic prints
James "Spider" Martin was an Alabama photojournalist known for his work documenting the American Civil Rights Movement. Collection comprises 44 black-and-white photographs, mostly 8x10 or 11x14 inches, documenting the March 1965 Selma to Montgomery voting rights marches. Subjects include civil rights leaders and march participants Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., Ralph Abernathy, James Bevel, Coretta Scott King, John Lewis, Bob Mants, Amelia Boynton Robinson, and Hosea Williams, as well as marchers, protesters, counter protesters with signs and Confederate flags, local police, and federal troops. Locations include the Brown Chapel A.M.E. Church in Selma; downtown Selma; the Edmund Pettus Bridge (site of the "Bloody Sunday" violence against protesters on March 7, 1965); Highway 80; downtown Montgomery; and the State Capitol grounds in Montgomery. Three related images are of Alabama governor George C. Wallace speaking during the 1968 U.S. presidential campaign. Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
Biographical / Historical
James "Spider" Martin was a photographer known for his work documenting the American Civil Rights Movement in 1965, specifically Bloody Sunday and the Selma to Montgomery March. He was born in 1939 in Fairfield, Alabama, and died in 2003 in Blount Springs, Alabama.
Conditions Governing Access
Collection is open for research
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Spider Martin photographs were received by the David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library as a purchase in 2020.
Related Materials
James Karales Photographs, 1953-2006 (photographs taken at civil rights marches)
SNCC Digital Gateway Project Files, 2002-2018 (bulk 2010-2018)
Content Description
Collection comprises 44 black-and-white images taken by Alabama-born photo journalist Spider Martin, documenting in detail the 1965 Selma to Montgomery voting rights marches. Subjects include civil rights leaders and march participants Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., speaking and marching; Ralph Abernathy; James Bevel; Coretta Scott King; John Lewis; Bob Mants; Amelia Boynton Robinson; and Hosea Williams. There are also images of marchers and protesters; counter protesters with signs and Confederate flags; musicians Peter, Paul, and Mary, and Harry Belafonte performing at the final rally in Montgomery; local and state police; and federal troops protecting the marchers. Many of these photographs became iconic images of the civil rights movement of the 1960s.
Locations include the Brown Chapel A.M.E. Church in Selma, downtown Selma, the Edmund Pettus Bridge (site of the "Bloody Sunday" violence against protesters on March 7, 1965), Highway 80 along which marchers walked, downtown Montgomery, and the State Capitol in Montgomery.
Additional related images are of Alamaba governor George C. Wallace speaking at rallies during his 1968 presidential campaign.
All of the prints were created via the gelatin silver process by Spider Martin, chiefly from 1993-1999 and some in 1965. Many are signed, and some bear handwritten captions, titles, commentary, and other marks in the photographer's hand. The donor's inventory also provided titles as well as contextual captions.
Acquired as part of the Archive of Documentary Arts at Duke University.
African American civil rights workers -- Photographs; African Americans -- Alabama -- Portraits; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Alabama -- 20th century; African Americans -- Civil rights -- History; African Americans -- Civil rights -- Press coverage; African Americans -- Suffrage; Civil rights demonstrations -- Alabama -- Montgomery -- 1960-1970 -- Photographs; Civil rights demonstrations -- Alabama -- Selma -- 1960-1970 -- Photographs; Civil rights movements -- Alabama -- History -- 20th century; Photographers -- Alabama; Photojournalists -- United States; Selma to Montgomery Rights March -- Photographs; Alabama -- Social conditions -- 20th century; Selma (Ala.) -- Photographs; Montgomery (Ala.) -- Photographs; Black-and-white photographs; Gelatin silver prints; Archive of Documentary Arts (Duke University); Martin, Spider, 1939-2003; King, Martin Luther, Jr., 1929-1968; Abernathy, Ralph David, 1926-; Lewis, John, 1940 February 21-; Robinson, Amelia Boynton, 1911-2015; Bevel, James L. (James Luther), 1936-2008; King, Coretta Scott, 1927-; Mants, Bob; Williams, Hosea, 1926-2000; Wallace, George C. (George Corley), 1919-1998; Turner, Albert, 1936-2000
- Selma to Montgomery Marches, 1965 March-August; 42 prints
  Arrangement
  Arranged chronologically
  Scope and Contents
  These images were taken by photographer Spider Martin of the Selma to Montgomery voting rights marches in 1965. The prints are arranged in rough chronological order, beginning with the first Voting Rights March from Selma in March 1965 and ending with Dr. Martin Luther King's speech in Birmingham, Alabama following the passage of the Voting Rights Act in August 1965. Many prints are signed by the photographer; a handful bear captions, titles, commentary in his hand, and other marks. Most of the prints were created by Martin in 1993 or 1995. They are all black-and-white (gelatin silver process) and measure 8x10 or 11x14 with the exception of two smaller prints.
  - Reflection of Brown Chapel AME Church as well as Spider Martin's in a reporter's sunglasses, Selma, Alabama, 1965 March; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0001)
    Title source: donor inventory.
  - Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. speaking at a rally at Brown Chapel A.M.E Church, Selma, Alabama, 1965 March; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0002)
    Signed on print verso with 1993 date. Front signed with 1995 date. Title source: donor inventory.
  - Majestic Café at Ben Moore Hotel, Selma, Alabama, 1965 March 17 (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0003)
    Marks: number on verso, 16. "The Ben Moore Hotel opened in 1951 offering safe lodging to Black travelers and was listed in the Green Book. It became a site for historic meetings between Civil Rights leaders where Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. was a regular customer of the Malden Brothers barbershop in the basement. The scene in this image is from the day when Dr. King led a voting rights march to the Montgomery Courthouse on March 17, 1965." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Two-minute warning, Selma March, Alabama, 1965 March; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0004)
    Marks, recto: "For weary feet, rested souls. --Townsend Davis," with other loan notes. "Alabama state troopers giving two minute warning to disperse to marchers led by John Lewis and Hosea Williams, who holds his nose in anticipation of tear gas." According to donor inventory, Martin's daughter, this print was made by Martin to send to clients; also, writing on front of print is in the hand of a friend of Martin's who helped manage the Selma to Montgomery Trail Study. Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Six hundred marchers make their way over the Edmund Pettus Bridge for the first march attempt to Montgomery, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0005)
  - Detail of an Alabama state trooper beating John Lewis during the attack against peaceful protesters on what became known as Bloody Sunday, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0006)
    Signed on print verso with 1993 date. Front signed with 1995 date. Note: "Spider later wrote, 'Lewis fell. Then the trooper picked him up and beat him again.'" Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Sheriff Jim Clark's mounted posse pursue marchers back over the bridge to Selma, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0007)
  - An Alabama state trooper beats John Lewis as other marchers run toward the Edmund Pettus Bridge during the attack on Bloody Sunday, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0008)
  - Marchers assist Amelia Boynton as troopers force the protest back over the bridge after the attack on Bloody Sunday, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0009)
  - Alabama state troopers form a roadblock on the far side of the Edmund Pettus Bridge for the second march, known as Turnaround Tuesday, 1965 March 9; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0010)
    "On March 9, 1965, Alabama state troopers form a roadblock on the far side of the Edmund Pettus Bridge for the second march, known as Turnaround Tuesday, in preparation to stand down marchers and return them back across the bridge to Selma." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Selma's Director of Public Safety, Wilson Baker, 1965 March 9; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0011)
    "Selma's Director of Public Safety, Wilson Baker, receives a telegram from a resident of Framingham, Massachusetts, reacting to news of the Bloody Sunday events." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - SCLC organizer, James Bevel and coordinator, James Orange, make their way through Lowndes County, Alabama down US Route 80, 1965 March 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0012)
    "SCLC organizer, James Bevel and coordinator, James Orange, make their way through Lowndes County, Alabama down US Route 80, also known as Jefferson Davis Memorial Highway, toward Montgomery with the marchers protesting for the right to vote." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Protesters leaving Lowndes County on 54 mile march to Montgomery, 1965 March 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0013)
  - March arrives in Montgomery, Alabama, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0014)
    "Amelia Boynton, John Lewis, Rosa Parks, Ralph Abernathy, Juanita Abernathy obscured by Andrew Young, Ralph Bunche, Martin Luther King, Jean Young, Coretta Scott King, Frederick Reese, and Hosea Williams, obscured by James Orange, lead march through downtown Montgomery, March 25, 1965." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Federal marshal H. Stanley Fountain meets Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and other march leaders at the foot of the Edmund Pettus Bridge, 1965 March 9; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0015)
    "Federal marshal H. Stanley Fountain meets Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. and other march leaders at the foot of the Edmund Pettus Bridge in downtown Selma to read the injunction prohibiting the second march. Charles Moore is photographer in back looking toward camera." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - A marcher holds the United States flag upside down, the signal for distress, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0016)
  - A billboard along the Selma to Montgomery March route, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0017)
    "A billboard along the Selma to Montgomery March route shows Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. at a 1957 event at the Highlander Folk School, an attempt to discredit King by associating him with communism." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - St. Jude campsite with Army patrol, 1965 March 24; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0018)
    "Last campsite of the march at the City of St. Jude where the Stars for Freedom Rally was held the night before the final leg into Montgomery with protection from US Army military police." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Mississippi Highway Patrolmen dispatched to Montgomery, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0019)
    "Mississippi Highway Patrolmen dispatched to Montgomery as backup force make their support of segregation clear as they watch the marchers arrive on March 25, 1965." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - Ralph Bunche, Dr. Martin Luther King Jr., Coretta Scott King, Rev. Frederick D. Reese and Hosea Williams lead the march through downtown Montgomery, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0020)
  - Marchers arriving into Montgomery, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0021)
    "25,000 marchers arriving into Montgomery at the end of the final march as speakers prepare to be seated at the foot of the Alabama state capitol." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - A counterprotester holds a sign at the closing rally for the Selma to Montgomery march, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 10 x 8 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0022)
  - State troopers form a barricade blocking the entrance to the state capitol, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0023)
  - Thousands gather before the Alabama State Capitol, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0024)
    Marks: verso, #3908 WP. "A crowd of 25,000 people listen to speeches outside the state capitol at the march's end." Title source: print verso. Note source: donor inventory.
  - Harry Belafonte, Joan Baez and Peter, Paul and Mary perform for the Montgomery crowd, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0025)
  - Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. speaks in Birmingham following the passage of the Voting Rights Act, 1965 August 12?; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0026)
  - Arms linked, Bob Mants, John Lewis, Hosea Williams, Andrew Young and other marchers pray outside Brown Chapel AME Church before beginning the March 7 march, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0029)
  - John Lewis, Hosea Williams, Albert Turner, Bob Mants and Charles Mauldin lead the first march across the Edmund Pettus Bridge, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0030)
  - An unconscious Amelia Boynton Robinson lies on the ground after a trooper beat her with his billy club, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0031)
    Marks: verso bears a second unidentified signature. Title source: donor inventory.
  - Alabama state troopers chase marchers back to Brown Chapel AME Church after the melee on Bloody Sunday, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0032)
  - Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. speaking at a rally at Brown Chapel AME Church in Selma, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0033)
  - Two-minute warning, Selma March, Alabama, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0034)
    "Alabama state troopers give a two minute warning to disperse to marchers led mby John Lewis and Hosea Williams, who holds his nose in anticipation of tear gas." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - A phalanx of Alabama state troopers file in line over and beyond the Edmund Pettus Bridge during the Selma March, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 3/4 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0035)
    Print is supported by original 11x14 black support board and sleeve. Title source: donor inventory.
  - Unidentified female student protester, 1965; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 6 3/4 x 10 1/2 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0036)
  - Selma rednecks, 1965 March 7; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0037)
    "At the foot of the Edmund Pettus Bridge, hecklers with a Confederate flag offer a counterprotest." A handwritten comment on the back of this print in the photographer's hand reads: "Selma Welcoming Committee / Selma March at the Foot of Edmund Pettus Bridge / These people called me a 'white nigger' (I considered that a compliment), one then spit on me and shot me the bird." Title source: print recto. First note source: donor inventory.
  - Rev. Ralph Abernathy and Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. during the first day of the march to Montgomery, 1965 March 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0038)
    "Rev. Ralph Abernathy and Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. during the first day of the march to Montgomery, March 21, 1965. Rev. Abernathy wears a lei, one of several airmailed to march leaders by a Hawaiian minister, Abraham Akaka." Title and note source: donor inventory. Handwritten note in the photographer's hand on the back of the print reads: "Dr. King knew he was a target. Many times I was tipped off that he might be assassinated. I look at this picture and think that Dr. King is looking towards Heaven and thinking that it is inevitable that he will die fighting for the struggle. I think of the gospel song 'Comin' Home.'"
  - Rev. Ralph Abernathy and Dr. Martin Luther King change their socks along march route after a long day marching to Montgomery, after 1965 March 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0039)
  - The march makes its way through Lowndes County under the protection of the federalized Alabama National Guard and US Army military police units, after 1965 March 21; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0040)
    Marks: Red ink stamps read "Crescent" and the numbers 3343 and 863009. Title source: donor inventory.
  - In the shadow of the Alabama state capitol, counterdemonstrators hold signs in protest at the closing rally for the Selma to Montgomery March, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0041)
  - Throngs of jubilant marchers arrive at the Alabama state capitol, 1965 March 25; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0042)
  - Dr. Martin Luther King Jr. listening to Rev. Ralph Abernathy speak at a rally at Montgomery's Beulah Baptist Church, 1965 March 16; Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 11 x 14 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0043)
- George Wallace Presidential Campaign, 1968; 3 prints
  - George Wallace speaking at a rally in Texas during his 1968 Presidential Campaign, Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0027)
    "Spider messaged his opinion of Wallace by laying a piece of paper he tore in the shape of a swastika on the print during exposure in the darkroom." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - George Wallace speaking at a rally in Texas during his 1968 Presidential Campaign, Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 8 x 10 inches (Box 1, Image RL.11783-P-0028)
    "A photograph made with a half-frame camera of George Wallace speaking at an outdoor rally in Texas during his 1968 Presidential Campaign tour." Title and note source: donor inventory.
  - George Wallace speaking at a rally at the Houston Astrodome during his 1968 Presidential Campaign tour, Gelatin silver print. Dimensions: 14 x 11 inches (Box 2, Image RL.11783-P-0044)